window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Discrete_Mathematics - Set_Theory — Slot 3 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Set_Theory — Slot 3",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>For the set N of natural numbers and a binary operation \\(f : N \\times N \\to N\\), an element \\(z \\in N\\) is called an identity for f, if f (a, z) = a = f(z, a), for all \\(a \\in N\\). Which of the following binary operations have an identity?<br>\ni. \\(f (x, y) = x + y - 3\\)<br>\nii. \\(f (x, y) = \\max(x, y)\\)<br>\niii. \\(f (x, y) = x^y\\)<br> <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I and II only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of these</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>I and II only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3539/gate2006-it-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>A set X can be represented by an array x[n] as follows <br> \\(x[i]=\\left\\{\\begin{matrix} 1 &amp;if  i\\in X \\\\ 0&amp;  otherwise \\end{matrix}\\right.\\) <br> Consider the following algorithm in which x,y and z are boolean arrays of size n;<pre><code>algorithm zzz(x[] , y[], z [])\n{\n   int i;\n   for (i=O; i &lt; n; ++i)\n         z[i] = (x[i] ^ ~y[i]) V (~x[i] ^ y[i])\n}</code></pre>\nThe set Z computed by the algorithm is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\((X\\cap Y)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\((X\\cup Y)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\((X-Y)\\cap(Y-X)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((X-Y)\\cup(Y-X)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((X-Y)\\cup(Y-X)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1828/gate2006-50#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Let S={1,2,3....,m},m \\(\\gt \\) 3. Let \\(X_{1},...,X_{n}\\) be subsets of S each of size 3.\nDefine a function f from S to the set of natural numbers as, f(i) is the number of sets \\(X_{j}\\) that contain the element i. That is \\(f(i)=|\\{j|i\\in X_{j}\\}|\\). Then \\(\\sum_{i=1}^{m}f(i)\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3m</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>3n</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2m+1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2n+1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>3n</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/988/gate2006-25#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Given a set of elements N = {1,2,...,n} and two arbitrary subsets A\\(\\subseteq\\)N and\nB\\(\\subseteq\\)N , how many of the n! permutations p from N to N satisfy min[p(A)]=min[p(B)], where min(S) is the smallest integer in the set of integers S and\np(S) is the set of integers obtained by applying permutation p to each element of S ? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\((n-|A\\cup B|)|A||B|\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\((|A|^{2}+|B|^{2})n^{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(n!(|A\\cap B|/|A\\cup B|)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(|A\\cap B|^{2}/\\binom{n}{|A\\cup B|^{2}}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(n!(|A\\cap B|/|A\\cup B|)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/987/gate2006-24#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Let E,F and G be finite sets.<br>\nLet X=(E \\(\\cap\\)F) - (F\\(\\cap\\)G) and Y = (E - (E\\(\\cap\\)G)) - (E - F).  <br> Which one of the\nfollowing is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(X\\subset Y\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(X\\supset Y\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>X=Y</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(X-Y\\neq \\phi\\) and \\(Y-X\\neq \\phi\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>X=Y</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/983/gate2006-22#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>We are given a set \\(X=\\{x_{1},...,x_{n}\\}\\) where \\(x_{i}=2^{i}\\). A sample \\(S\\subseteq X\\)  is drawn by selecting each   \\(x_{i}\\) independently with probability \\(p_{i}=\\frac{1}{2}\\). The expected value of the smallest number in sample S is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1/n</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\sqrt{n}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>n</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>n</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/979/gate2006-18#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Let X, Y, Z be sets of sizes x, y and z respectively. Let W=X\\(\\times\\)Y and E be the\nset of all subsets of W. The number of functions from Z to E is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(Z^{2xy}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(Z*2^{xy}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(Z^{2x+y}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2^{xyz}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2^{xyz}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/881/gate2006-2#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(n = p^{2}q\\), where p and q are distinct prime numbers. How many numbers m satisfy \\(1 \\leq m \\leq n\\) and gcd(m,n)=1? <br>Note that gcd(m,n) is the greatest common divisor of m and n. <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(p(q - 1)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(pq\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\left ( p^{2}-1 \\right ) (q - 1)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(p(p - 1) (q - 1)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(p(p - 1) (q - 1)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3780/gate2005-it-34\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Let A be a set with n elements. Let C be a collection of distinct subsets of A such that for any two subsets \\(S_1\\) and \\(S_2\\) in C, either \\(S_1 \\subset S_2\\) or \\(S_2\\subset S_1\\). What is the maximum cardinality of C? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>n</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>n+1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{n-1} + 1\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>n!</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>n+1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3779/gate2005-it-33\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Let A, B and C be non-empty sets and let<br>\nX = (A - B) - C and Y = (A - C) - (B - C) <br>\nWhich one of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>X=Y</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>X\\(\\subset\\)Y</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Y\\(\\subset\\)X</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of these</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>X=Y</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1157/gate2005-8#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>In a class of 200 students, 125 students have taken Programming Language course, 85 students have taken Data Structures course, 65 students have taken Computer Organization course; 50 students have taken both Programming Language and Data Structures, 35 students have taken both Programming Language and Computer Organization; 30 students have taken both Data Structures and Computer Organization, 15 students have taken all the three courses.How many students have not taken any of the three courses? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>15</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>20</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>25</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>30</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>25</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3643/gate2004-it-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Let P(S) denotes the power set of set S. Which of the following is always true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2000)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(P(P(S)) = P(S)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(P(S) \\cap P(P(S)) = \\{ \\emptyset \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(P(S) \\cap S = P(S)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(S \\notin P(S)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(P(S) \\cap P(P(S)) = \\{ \\emptyset \\}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/653/gate2000-2-6\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>A partial order \\(\\leq\\) is defined on the set \\(S=\\left \\{ x, a_1, a_2, \\ldots, a_n, y \\right \\} \\text{ as }x \\leq _{i} a_{i}\\) for all \\(i\\) and \\(a_{i}\\leq y\\) for all i, where \\(n \\geq 1\\). The number of total orders on the set S which contain the partial order \\(\\leq\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>n!</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>n+2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>n</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>n!</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2257/gate1997-6-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Given \\(\\Sigma=\\{a,b\\}\\), which one of the following sets is not countable? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Set of all strings over \\(\\Sigma\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Set of all languages over \\(\\Sigma\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Set of all regular languages over \\(\\Sigma\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Set of all languages over \\(\\Sigma\\) accepted by Turing machines</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Set of all languages over \\(\\Sigma\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2235/gate1997-3-4\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(X = \\{2, 3, 6, 12, 24\\}\\), Let \\(\\leq\\) be the partial order defined by \\(X \\leq Y\\) if x divides y. Number of edges in the Hasse diagram of \\((X, \\leq)\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>9</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>4</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2706/gate1996-1-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
